{"tossups": [{"question": "After the dramatic final hours of this year's presidential election, a reporter phoned the loser and was told \"the president is asleep,\" to which he responded, \"When he wakes up, tell him he isn't the president.\" That loser in this year, Associate Justice of the Supreme Court Charles Evans Hughes, was the Republican candidate, and the Democratic candidate in this year ran on the slogan \u201cHe Kept Us out of War.\" For ten points, name this presidential election year in which a second electoral victory was won by Woodrow Wilson.", "answer": "<b><u>1916</u></b>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "This character appeared in a black-and-white serial in 1944 but differs from the original Timely Comics character, appearing instead as District Attorney Grant Gardner. After this Joe Simon creation was controversially depicted punching a national leader, New York mayor Fiorello La Guardia personally contacted the creators in support. In continuous publication since having been revived in 1964, for ten points, who is this super soldier played by Chris Evans in the Marvel Cinematic Universe who carries a shield and steadfastly defends the U.S.?", "answer": "<b><u>Captain America</u></b> (accept Steve <b><u>Rogers</u></b>)", "metadata": "Trash - Trash"}, {"question": "Konrad I, Duke of Mazovia, bequeathed land to this group in modern day Chelmno to ward off pagan raids. Alexander Nevsky\u2019s victory in the Battle of the Ice, fought on a frozen Lake Peipus [[PAY-pus]], led to this group renouncing their claims on Russia. This order's supreme office was called a Hochmeister [[HOKE-mai-stehr]], and it lost much of its Baltic land after a Polish-Lithuanian force defeated it at Grunwald. For ten points, name this Catholic crusading order of German Knights.", "answer": "<b><u>Teutonic</u></b> Knights (or Order of <b><u>Brothers of the German House of Saint Mary in</u></b> <b><u>Jerusalem</u></b>; accept <b><u>Teutonic</u></b> Order)", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "This artist depicted a protest against the removal of Maria Luisa\u2019s children to France in a painting that shows a group of Turkish soldiers wielding scimitars and daggers attacking a crowd. This artist\u2019s painting <em>The Charge of the Mamelukes</em> is the companion to his painting showing a man in a white shirt and yellow pants holding his hands up in front of a firing squad. For ten points, what Spanish artist depicted Napoleon\u2019s occupation of his homeland in <em>The Third of May 1808</em>?", "answer": "Francisco <b><u>Goya</u></b>", "metadata": "Fine Arts - Visual Fine Arts"}, {"question": "This company competed with Kroman and sponsored the <em>Cavalcade of Sports</em> program. Magnetic double-edged blades and escape maps were hidden in this company's equipment for P.O.W. escapees, and William Emery Nickerson helped design this company's devices. During World War One, this company developed the Khaki Set for use by soldiers, outstripping their competitors as their products did not require stropping. King Camp founded, for ten points, what company that merged into Proctor and Gamble which still sells shaving devices under their brand?", "answer": "The <b><u>Gillette</u></b> Company", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "Toward the end of this man\u2019s reign, a meteor was found inscribed with the prophecy of his death, leading him to kill everyone nearby. A musician who had been blinded by this ruler attempted to assassinate him with a lute which had been weighted with lead. This man was killed by another heavy metal prescribed for him by his team of alchemists as an \"Elixir of Immortality.\" For ten points, name this conqueror of Chu who became the first emperor of China.", "answer": "<b><u>Qin Shi Huang</u></b> Di (or <b><u>Ying</u></b> Zheng; accept <b><u>Zheng</u></b>, King of Qin; accept <b><u>Zhao</u></b>; accept <b><u>Huangdi</u></b>; accept <b><u>Qin</u></b>)", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {"question": "This musician, together with saxophonist Paul Gonzalves. allegedly caused a riot at the 1956 Newport Jazz Festival with their performance of \"Diminuendo and Crescendo in Blue.\" This frequent performer at the Cotton Club described the role of slavery and the church in Black American history in his suite <em>Black, Brown, and Beige</em>. This artist made what is considered the first significant African-American film score for 1959's <em>Anatomy of a</em> <em>Murder</em>, created with Billy Strayhorn. For ten points, name this legendary jazz pianist and band leader.", "answer": "Edward \"Duke\" <b><u>Ellington</u></b>", "metadata": "Fine Arts - Other Fine Arts - Jazz"}, {"question": "One member of this family promoted the terrible singing of his wife, Ganna Walska [[HAWN-ah WAHL-skah]], which Orson Welles claimed inspired the screenplay of <em>Citizen</em> <em>Kane</em>. The Brazilian embassy in the U.S. is housed in a manor once owned by this family. One member of this family invented a device he called a \"hemp-break.\" This family owned the <em>Chicago Tribune</em> for much of the 20th century, and a member of this family invented the mechanical reaper. For ten points, name this family which merged its company with Deering to form International Harvester.", "answer": "<b><u>McCormick</u></b> (accept Harold <b><u>McCormick</u></b>; accept Robert <b><u>McCormick</u></b>, Jr.)", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "Rebel Herero warriors were forced to cross this desert into British lands after the German Empire won the Battle of Waterberg in 1904. The homeland of the San [[SAHN]] People stretches across this desert, and the San are sometimes known as the \u201cBushmen\" of this desert. In 1997 the San and the Bakgalagadi were evicted from their land in this desert after De Beers determined the Gope diamond mines were valuable, but in 2006, the Botswana High Court ruled that their eviction from this desert was unlawful. For ten points, name this large desert of southern Africa.", "answer": "<b><u>Kalahari</u></b> Desert", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {"question": "The original creator of this product had a son who caused a diplomatic crisis in Haiti after suspending President Philippe Sudr\u00e9 Dartiguenave's [[dar-tee-geh-NAHVS]] salary. One tycoon who sold this food introduced <em>coypu</em> into his state and founded a colony for egrets called Bird City. The <em>Charlie Ration Cookbook</em> was made by a producer of this product for which Maunsel White had a similar recipe. This foodstuff is made in Avery Island by the McIlhenny [[MAK-ill-hen-ee]] Company. For ten points, name this spicy chili pepper sauce whose name is derived from a Mexican state.", "answer": "<b><u>Tabasco</u></b> Sauce", "metadata": "Current Events - Current Events"}, {"question": "Anton\u00edn Dvo\u0159\u00e1k [[DVOR-jahk] premiered his American string quartet at this event, having composed it during his time among Czech immigrants in Iowa. Frederick Jackson Turner first argued his \u201cFrontier Thesis\u201d in a lecture given at this event. One of the stars on a Midwestern city's flag represents this 19th century event, whose fairgrounds were designed by Frederick Law Olmstead. For ten points, name this 1893 World's Fair held in Chicago and named for the anniversary of a Genoan explorer's rediscovery of the New World.", "answer": "World's <b><u>Columbian Expo</u></b>sition (accept World's Fair: <b><u>Columbian Expo</u></b>sition, <b><u>1893 World's Fair</u></b> before mentioned, or <b><u>Chicago World</u></b>'s Fair or <b><u>Chicago World</u></b>'s Exposition before \"Chicago\" is mentioned; prompt on \"World's Fair\" or \"World Fair\")", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {}, {"question": "This politician's father resigned his Senate seat in 2002 to become his state's governor and appointed this person to fill the seat. In 2010, this senator ran a successful write-in campaign after being defeated in the Republican primary by Joe Miller. Donald Trump promised to campaign against this politician in the 2022 midterms in retaliation for her vote to convict during his second impeachment. In 2018, this politician was the only Republican senator to not vote for Brett Kavanaugh's confirmation. For ten points, name this female senator from Alaska.", "answer": "Lisa Ann <b><u>Murkowski</u></b>", "metadata": "Current Events - Current Events"}, {}, {"question": "A pope with this name commissioned Pinturicchio [[pin-too-REE-kee-oh]] to decorate his namesake apartments in the Apostolic Palace. Anselm of Baggio [[BAH-zhyo]] served as the second pope of this name, calling for the Crusade of Barbastro against the Moors. The seventh pope of this name provided sanctuary to the exiled Christina, Queen of Sweden. The sixth pope of this name, a man of Aragonese [[ah-rah-go-NEH-seh]] descent, excommunicated Girolamo Savonarola and confirmed the rights of Spain to their New World claims. For ten points, give this papal name of Rodrigo Borgia [[BOR-zhah]].", "answer": "<b><u>Alexander</u></b>", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {}, {"question": "Oil workers in this state were depicted in the documentary <em>The Overnighters</em>. The opening of the Parshall oil field led to an oil boom in this state from 2006 to 2014 which included horizontal drilling and damaging hydraulic fracking. The 1997 Red River Flood severely damaged this state's city of Grand Forks. This state was formerly home to the \"divorce capital\" of the Midwest at its largest city of Fargo. For ten points, name this upper Midwest U.S. state.", "answer": "<b><u>North Dakota</u></b>", "metadata": "Geography - Geography"}, {}, {"question": "This scientist's views were criticized in the Blockhead and Chinese Room thought experiments. This scientist may have committed suicide by injecting cyanide into an apple. This scientist names a 2017 law that retroactively pardons British men convicted of homosexuality. This scientist's namesake machine is an idealized computer which reads symbols from an infinite tape. For ten points, name this computer scientist who names a test that distinguishes between humans and machines.", "answer": "Alan <b><u>Turing</u></b>", "metadata": "Philosophy - Philosophy"}, {}, {"question": "One of this artist's works was commissioned to honor soldiers who were killed fighting the Central Powers at T\u00e2rgu Jiu [[tehr-goo-ZHEE-ooh]]. That work, his Sculptural Ensemble, includes his <em>The Gate of the Kiss</em> and <em>Endless Column</em>. This artist carved a marble sculpture of a head titled <em>Sleeping Muse</em>, and the Salon des Ind\u00e9pendants removed this artist's sculpture <em>Princess X</em> for its allegedly phallic appearance. For ten points, name this groundbreaking Romanian sculptor, a pioneer of modernism.", "answer": "Constantin <b><u>Br\u00e2ncu\u0219i</u></b> [[brin-KOOSH]]", "metadata": "Fine Arts - Visual Fine Arts"}, {}, {"question": "Father Georgy Gapon led over 50 thousand demonstrators outside this site to protest autocracy, leading to hundreds dying from Imperial fire in the Bloody Sunday Massacre. For ten points, name this Imperial residence in Saint Petersburg, built by Peter the Great.", "answer": "<b><u>Sheep</u> </b>  An unswept chimney led to a destructive 1837 fire at this site, which occurred while (8)  the Imperial court was at Mikhailovsky Theatre. A Sergei Eisenstein film culminated in the storming of this structure by the Red Guard in 1917. Father Georgy Gapon led over 50 thousand demonstrators outside this site to protest autocracy, leading to hundreds dying from Imperial fire in the Bloody Sunday Massacre. For ten points, name this Imperial residence in Saint Petersburg, built by Peter the Great.  ANSWER: <b><u>Winter Palace</u></b> (or <b><u>Zimnij dvorets</u></b>)", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {}, {"question": "<b><u>This city's lace industry inspired the series</u> </b><em><b><u>Thread Routes</u></b></em><b><u>, and this city's</u></b> <b><u>Church of Our Lady contains Michelangelo's</u> </b><em><b><u>Madonna and Child</u></b></em><b><u>. Erich Korngold</u></b> <b><u>situated his opera</u> </b><em><b><u>The Dead City</u></b></em><b><u> in this city where the first English book was printed</u></b> <b><u>by William Caxton. The site of the (+)</u> Matins [[mah-TANH]] massacre, this city's Bourse stock exchange was likely the world's first. The center of the 13th century (*) </b>wool industry in Western Europe and home to the Golden Inlet, for ten points, what is this capital of West Flanders in Belgium?", "answer": "<b><u>Bruges</u></b> [[BROOZH]] (or <b><u>Brugge</u></b>)", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "<b><u>Following his death, this musician was worshipped as a god and later a saint at</u></b> <b><u>the Yardbird Temple in San Francisco. In 2018, this musician's long-lost album</u> </b><em><b><u>Both</u></b></em> <em><b><u>Directions at Once</u></b></em><b><u> was recovered. A Jazz Hall of Famer, this man received a</u></b> <b><u>posthumous Grammy in (*)</u> 1982 for his album </b><em><b>Bye, Bye Blackbird</b></em><b>. With Cannonball Adderley, this musician played the (*) </b>saxophone for Miles Davis's landmark album <em>Kind</em> <em>of Blue</em>. For ten points, name this influential jazz saxophonist, who recorded the albums <em>Giant Steps</em> and <em>A Love Supreme</em>.", "answer": "John <b><u>Coltrane</u></b>", "metadata": "Fine Arts - Other Fine Arts - Jazz"}, {"question": "<b><u>ABA head Frank J. Hogan rebuked this man on radio who was almost indicted</u></b> <b><u>for sedition by Francis Biddle. Michael Gallagher's support for this man eventually</u></b> <b><u>forced the government to restrict his free speech rights. This man, who coined the</u></b> <b><u>term \"Roosevelt (*)</u> or Ruin,\" published the far-right periodical </b><em><b>Social Justice</b></em><b>, which among other things, claimed there was a Jewish plot to run America. The founder of the National Shrine of the Little Flower in (*) </b>Detroit, for ten points, who was this New Deal-era Catholic priest who supported the Axis?", "answer": "Father Charles <b><u>Coughlin</u></b>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "<b><u>This man was named \"The Red King\" and Mormaer [[MORE-mare]] of Moray</u></b> <b><u>after the death of a man nicknamed \"the Unfortunate.\" After fighting Godwin of Essex,</u></b> <b><u>this man who introduced feudalism to (+)</u> Scotland, was killed at the Battle of Lumphanan [[loom-FAH-nahn]] and was succeeded by Lulach [[LOO-lock]], who was killed by Malcolm III. Raphael Holinshed's [[HALL-in-sheds]] works inspired a (*) </b>playwright to tell this man's story which included the Three Witches. For ten points, name this man who is killed by MacDuff in Shakespeare's rendition of the story of this ill-fated king.", "answer": "<b><u>Macbeth</u></b> (or <b><u>Mac Beth</u></b>ad mac Findla\u00edch)", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "<b><u>This event was precipitated by the response to the Bhola Cyclone, which killed</u></b> <b><u>half a million people, leading Maulana Bhashani to call for one prime minister\u2019s</u></b> <b><u>resignation. Pakistani president Zulfikar Ali Bhutto orchestrated the (+)</u> Delhi Agreement, which ended this conflict. Under President Yahya Khan, Pakistani forces began this war after committing Operation Searchlight, a mass killing of (*) </b>Bengali citizens. For ten points, name this armed conflict which led to the sovereignty of a nation with capital at Dhaka.", "answer": "<b><u>Bangladesh Liberation War</u></b> (or <b><u>Bangladesh War of Independence</u></b>; prompt on \"Liberation War\" or \"War of Independence\")", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {"question": "<b><u>This leader has been accused of passing pork barrel legislation after having a</u></b> <b><u>4,000-seat stadium built a few meters from his countryside home. While leader of the</u></b> <b><u>opposition, this politician staged protests after PM Ferenc Gyurcs\u00e1ny [[FEHR-ents</u></b> <b><u>DOOHR-chahn]] gave a profanity-laden speech to his party. This former professional</u></b> <b><u>(+)</u> footballer built a border wall to combat illegal immigration between his nation and southern neighbor (*) </b>Serbia. For ten points, name this prime minister of Hungary, the leader of the conservative Fidesz [[FEE-dess]] Party.", "answer": "Viktor <b><u>Orban</u></b>", "metadata": "Current Events - Current Events"}, {"question": "<b><u>Jacques Massu evoked this government\u2019s name for his short-lived 1950s</u></b> <b><u>military junta during the Algiers Putsch. This government was created by the</u></b> <b><u>National Convention to supplement the Committee of General Defence and was</u></b> <b><u>initially led by perfume dealer Maximin Isnard, a (+)</u> Girondist, until his 1793 flight from Paris. This government was deposed during the Thermidorian Reaction, and it ruled at the height of the (*) </b>\u201cReign of Terror.\u201d For ten points, name this \u201cCommittee\u201d during the French Revolution led by Maximilian Robespierre.", "answer": "Committee of <b><u>Public Safety</u></b> (or Comit\u00e9 de <b><u>salut public</u></b>)", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "<b><u>During this court case, Associate Justice Frank Murphy introduced the word</u></b> <b><u>\u201cracism\u201d into the Supreme Court lexicon. John Roberts specifically repudiated the</u></b> <b><u>decision made during this court case by the Harlan Stone-led court in the decision of</u></b> <b><u>the 2018 case (*)</u> </b><em><b>Trump v. Hawaii</b></em><b>. This case upheld the stipulations of Executive Order 9066, created by Franklin D. Roosevelt in reaction to the (*) </b>bombing of Pearl Harbor. For ten points, name this 1944 court case upholding Japanese internment during World War Two.", "answer": "<em><b><u>Korematsu</u></b> v. United States</em>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "<b><u>Before this battle, Ian Hamilton was appointed to command the</u></b> <b><u>Mediterranean Expeditionary Force, but their failures ended his military career and</u></b> <b><u>led to the resignation of the First Lord of Admiralty. ANZAC Day honors the lost lives</u></b> <b><u>of troops from (+)</u> Australia and New Zealand during this campaign, and the future \"Father of Turkey,\" Kemal Atat\u00fcrk, repelled British offensives at (*) </b>Scimitar Hill during this campaign. For ten points, name this World War One campaign named for a Turkish peninsula, a costly attempt by the Allies to control the Dardanelles.", "answer": "<b><u>Gallipoli</u></b> Campaign (accept Battle of <b><u>Gallipoli</u></b>)", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {}], "bonuses": []}